Today's דף daf is כ"ג chaf-gimmel and we're still a little bit
behind, hopefully we'll catch up soon. We pick up on the משנה
Mishna in כ"ב עמוד ב' chaf-bet amud bet about six lines down
in the wide lines. We've just done with the, we've now covered
קידושי אישה, Kiddushei isha, יבום, yibum, and עבד עברי. eved Ivri. So
we're going from קניינים kinyanim for free people, and עבד עברי eved
Ivri is this interesting middle state, right? It's to some degree like
a שכיר sachir and to some degree there might be חסרון chasron
of a קניין הגוף. kinyan haguf. And now we go to עבד
כנעני, eved Knaani, which is certainly considered fully property. You put something
on my, not on my עבד כנעני eved Knaani and it's like
you put it on my property, it's like I קונה kona it
with a קניין חצר, kinyan chatzer, so it's on the one hand
it's like property. On the other hand, the תורה Torah insists and
the revolution of the תורה Torah is that he's still a human
being and he goes free if you mistreat him, if you poke
out an eye or a tooth. Times where the master could even
be חייב מיתה chayav misa and so on. So that's the status
of an עבד כנעני. eved Knaani. Now we, so that's the next
one we move to. עבד כנעני נקנה בכסף ובשטר ובחזקה, Eved Knaani
nikneh bekeseph uvishtar uvichazaka, an עבד כנעני eved Knaani is purchased, is
acquired through money, שטר, shtar, a document, and חזקה, chazaka, and taking
חזקה chazaka is a way of right, of mastering, of showing ownership
which we'll see what that means in the גמרא. Gemara. Basically, it's
having him perform an act of service to you. Now that is
the same as the גמרא Gemara is going to immediately say of
קרקע, karka, so there you again see the comparison to just other
types of property. And it's also worth noting that the חזקה chazaka
was not present by the עבד עברי. eved Ivri. So חזקה, chazaka,
which is the most that is demonstrative of a sense of taking
something as a piece of property under my control, is specifically by
עבד כנעני eved Knaani and not by עבד עברי. eved Ivri. וקונה
את עצמו בכסף על ידי אחרים, Vekoneh et atzmo bekeseph al yedei
acheirim, he can get his own freedom if other people give money
to the master to free him. And that can't be forced on
the master, but if the master agrees, but it's other people, not
he himself, because we'll see in the גמרא Gemara there's a whole
question of whether it's even possible for an עבד כנעני eved Knaani
to own his own property and to own his own money. But
if other people pay for his freedom and the master agrees, he
goes free. ובשטר על ידי עצמו, Uvishtar al yedei atzmo, or if
the master, I'm understanding that, how
it would be על ידי
אחרים? al yedei acheirim? Meaning he bought him, he owns it?
No, I go and I feel bad for this עבד. eved.
In other words,
you and the עבד eved you mean? Yeah, either I feel bad
for the עבד eved or I make a deal, if I free
you then will you agree to pay me back once you get
free or something of that nature. And then I pay the master
the money and the master agrees to free him for the money
I'm paying the master.
But it could be any money he wants.
Right, it's totally up to the master, but it's the same way
כסף קידושין keseph kiddushin could be any money that the woman wants.
But if the master agrees to free him by accepting money for
him, then whatever that agreed upon money is, once that money changes
hands, he goes free. ובשטר, Uvishtar, and a writ of manumission, a
שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, you write הרי אתה בן חורין harey ata
ben chorin and you give it to the slave, על ידי עצמו,
al yedei atzmo, delivered directly to the slave. דברי רבי מאיר, Divrei
Rabbi Meir, that's what Rabbi Meir says. Does that mean to exclude
deliver to other people or not? We'll see in the
גמרא. Gemara. וחכמים אומרים בכסף על ידי עצמו, Vechachamim omrim bekeseph al
yedei atzmo, and the
sages say by money even he can free himself,
money again if the master agrees, ובשטר על ידי אחרים, uvishtar al
yedei acheirim,
and by a writ given to other people. Does it mean only
give it to other people, not given to him? That would be
strange. Anyway, we'll see about that in the גמרא. Gemara. ובלבד שיהיה
הכסף משל אחרים. Uvilvad sheyihye hakeseph mishel acheirim.
But even when he is redeeming himself from money that he is
giving, it has to be other people's money. Now what does that
mean, other people's money? Presumably it means that any money he earns,
or if he finds a lost object, that automatically would belong to
his master. No way he can pocket that. But if somebody gave
him a gift of money, and on the condition or on the
assumption that it would be just for him, that's a way he
could have his own money. So it's his own money he's giving
his master, but it's money that came from other people. So is
it contradicting itself? על ידי עצמו Al yedei atzmo and
כסף משל
אחרים.
keseph
mishel acheirim. It's
על ידי עצמו, al yedei atzmo, he pays the money, but it
came from other people. If he earned the money himself, it's not
his money, it goes straight to his master. If somebody else gave
him the money, and gave him the money let's say even explicitly
that he should own it and not his master, that's then he
is paying the money himself, but it originated from other people or
it came from other people.
Wouldn't you think that's פשיטא pshita if it
came from
someone who said it's only for you?
No, because we're going to see that according to the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma even in that case he can't own the money. Okay,
we'll see all this in the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, מנאלן, minalan, now
where do you know this from? דכתיב, dechtiv, מנאלן minalan let's first
start with כסף שטר חזקה keseph shtar chazaka before we get to
the more complicated כסף keseph discussions. דכתיב, dechtiv, והתנחלתם אתם לבניכם אחריכם,
vehisnachalem otam livneichem achareichem, you shall bequeath them, these slaves, to your
children after
you, לרשת אחוזה lareshet achuza for to inherit as an אחוזה, achuza,
what's a good word. inheritance but more anyway it's sort of like
an ancestral type of inheritance.
So הקישן הכתוב לשדה אחוזה Hikishan hakatuv lesde achuzah just like an
ancestral field. That's the אחוזה. achuzah. מה שדה אחוזה Mah sde achuzah
the same way this ancestral field or just field קרקע karka נקנה
בכסף בשטר ובחזקה nikna bechesef bishtar ubechazakah is acquired as we're going
to see when we get to the next משנה Mishna by three
things money a writ and חזקה chazakah so this act of taking
possession אף עבד כנעני נקנה בכסף בשטר ובחזקה. af eved kenaani nikna
bechesef bishtar ubechazakah. So again that makes it as you probably are
aware that throughout ש"ס Shas is a discussion about an עבד כנעני
eved kenaani being compared to קרקע karka for various הלכות halachot in
which there's exceptions in terms of things that are קרקע. karka. And
here very clearly is this comparison being made and to demonstrate how
the act of possession is taking place which again really underscores this
idea of עבד כנעני eved kenaani is now we're dealing with something
that really is treated as property. Okay so כסף שטר וחזקה. Kesef
Shtar veChazakah. Now אי מה שדה אחוזה חוזרת לבעלים ביובל ee mah
sdeh achuzah chozeret livaalim beYovel one
minute but when you buy a field of an ancestral field it
goes back to the owners in the יובל Yovel אף עבד כנעני
חוזר לבעלים ביובל af eved kenaani chozer livaalim beYovel
maybe that goes back let's say you bought it from a non-Jew.
Question is how did the original person own the עבד כנעני eved
kenaani to sell it to you? But anyway let's say that in
whatever that person is if the person is a Jew or non-Jew
sells you this עבד כנעני eved kenaani maybe it goes back. It
would be a question does that mean he would go free ביובל
beYovel or just go back to the original owner? But anyway either
way that's the הוה אמינא hava amina תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar לעולם
בהם תעבודו. Leolam bahem taavodu. No
you should work for them forever
and there there's although לעולם leolam by עבד עברי eved Ivri meant
he goes free ביובל beYovel here there's no פסוק pasuk to indicate
that so it means that they do not have that הלכה. halacha.
It's a permanent sale but it's like קרקע karka it's acquired by
כסף שטר וחזקה. Kesef Shtar veChazakah. Now we'll see in a minute
what חזקה chazakah is. תנא Tana now but then to what now
we're going to focus on other possible means of acquisition which again
underscore the question of of the עבד eved being similar to just
standard property. תנא Tana אף בחליפין. Af bechalipin. He can even be
acquired through חליפין chalipin right you exchange you give something in exchange
for the עבד eved or you do the handkerchief which is more
even a symbolic type of a thing and then through that you
know the owner takes the takes the handkerchief and then the עבד
eved now belongs to the other person. The original owner takes the
handkerchief and now the עבד eved belongs to the other person.
Okay so ותנא דידן Vetana didan
our תנא Tana why did he not mention חליפין? chalipin? מילתא דליתא
במטלטלין קתני מילתא דאיתא במטלטלין לא קתני Milta de-leita be-metaltelin katani milta
de-ita be-metaltelin lo katani
because he wanted to emphasize the ways in which it's similar to
קרקע karka because that's explicit in the פסוק. pasuk. Although קרקע karka
is also acquired by חליפין chalipin that's true חליפין chalipin works both
by קרקע karka and by מטלטלין metaltelin it doesn't work by אשה
ishah remember right but it works again an interesting difference this also
highlights the way in which this is more property חליפין chalipin doesn't
work by אשה ishah but חליפין chalipin does work by קרקע karka
and מטלטלין. metaltelin. Nevertheless our משנה Mishna wanted to mention the things
that were distinctive to קרקע karka and not מטלטלין. metaltelin. But it
is true it also works for מטלטלין. metaltelin. מילתא דליתא במטלטלין קתני
מילתא דאיתא במטלטלין לא קתני Milta de-leita be-metaltelin katani milta de-ita be-metaltelin
lo katani it only wanted to mention things that were not a
מטלטלין metaltelin something that is a מטלטלין metaltelin לא קתני lo katani
it didn't want to mention but you know what that's also true
presumably because now the question is is this because an עבד eved
is like מטלטלין metaltelin or is this because an עבד eved is
like קרקע karka but חליפין chalipin also works for קרקע. karka. Let's
work with that assumption for now that it's still the קרקע karka
comparison. Okay אמר שמואל Amar Shmuel but now we're going to go
even further says שמואל Shmuel עבד כנעני נקנה במשיכה. Eved kenaani nikna
bimshichah.
Now this is clearly treating him like מטלטלין metaltelin can be acquired
by dragging him towards you that's something that only works by מטלטלין.
metaltelin. כיצד Keitzad
how is that true? תקפו ובאו Takpo uvao you grab hold of
him and you schlep him towards you קנאו knao then you acquire
him. קראו ובא Karao uva but if you called him hey come
here and he came לא קנאו lo knao you did not acquire
him because that did not show you're not in the end he
is choosing to listen to you. So it's not showing that you
are taking him under your control right I can call you and
you can come to me.
Yeah but it's still well okay
but it's still well that might be you're talking more like a
חזקה chazakah type of a thing anyway the point is is that
it's not you are pulling him towards you he is choosing. So
the גמרא Gemara says now בשלמא לתנא דידן Bishlama letana didan
now we get why our תנא Tana did not mention משיכה mshichah
if שמואל Shmuel is right that משיכה mshichah works because מילתא דאיתא
במטלטלין לא קתני milta de-ita be-metaltelin lo katani he didn't want to
mention things that existed by מטלטלין. metaltelin. Okay and only want to
mention things that are only by קרקע. karka. דליתא
במטלטלין קתני. De-leita be-metaltelin katani. אלא לתנא ברא Ela letana bara
but the תנא Tana who mentioned
חליפין chalipin who's also mentioning things that work by מטלטלין metaltelin ניתני
משיכה nisni mshichah why not mention משיכה mshichah as well? כי קתני
מילתא דאיתא בין במקרקעי בין במטלטלי. Ki katani milta de-ita bein bimkarkei
bein bimetalteli. Even that other תנא Tana mentioned things that were still
limited his list to things that were true by קרקע. karka. He
was willing to include in his list things that worked for קרקע
karka and מטלטלין metaltelin but still his list were things that worked
by
קרקע. karka. a question about what you're going to put on, what
you're going to mention, but everybody agrees. Of course, one could wonder
really is it true that everybody agrees to all of these? And
particularly שמואל's Shmuel innovation is to treat an עבד Eved like a
form of מטלטלין. Mataltelin. Now I have to say, you know, partly
that could be because of the unique nature of the עבד, Eved,
meaning the real question is why is an עבד Eved like קרקע?
Karka? Right, what's distinctive about קרקע Karka is that it doesn't move.
Something that actually moves, right, is something that you could have other
ways of showing your control. You bring it into your, onto your
property, you know, you draw it, you lift it up. Something like
קרקע, Karka, right, which doesn't move, you can't pull it, put it
somewhere that it now shows that it's yours, so you have to
do something either external to it, כסף, Kesef, שטר, Shtar, maybe חליפין,
Chalipin, or you do something where it is to show your mastery
but not by, you know, taking it onto you. So that's the
חזקה. Chazakah. You do some act. So you, so if you had
to ask me, well, which things are more possible to do by
an עבד, Eved, it's the מטלטלין Mataltelin type of קניינים, Kinyanim, right?
So why would you go to the קרקע Karka one? Now, which
raises the question: why is an עבד Eved linked to קרקע? Karka?
Presumably, I mean, if somebody has a better reason, I'm happy to
hear it, but the only sort of, you know, reason, presumably it's
because while the classic use of עבדים Avadim were in the fields,
right, so they're sort of seen as one with the קרקע, Karka,
like connected to the field. Now, of course, you could have domestic
slaves as well, but again, maybe, I don't know, they're somehow seen
as attached to the house. Anyway, right, I mean, that's true, but
an ox is still מטלטלין, Mataltelin, so that doesn't, it's not a
full explanation. So the other possibility, which then highlights... so anyway, from
that approach, you understand the reasonableness of שמואל's Shmuel position. Maybe they
have an element like קרקע, Karka, but you know, they're also movable,
so why should we exclude the normal קניינים Kinyanim that you have
by מטלטלין? Mataltelin? By the way, there actually is a debate in
the גמרא Gemara whether עבד Eved is כקרקע דמי Ke-karka dami or
not כקרקע דמי, Ke-karka dami, not by קניינים Kinyanim but by other
types of issues, like when certain הלכות Halachot exclude land, like questions
about גניבה Gineiva or other כפל, Kefel, other types of questions, are
עבדים Avadim excluded as well? Okay, so one idea is, yeah, they're
also like מטלטלין, Mataltelin, you can also move them. But another way
of thinking about it, which makes I think, which gets to maybe
a core issue here is, the more you treat something as chattel,
the more you completely make it like just a piece of property.
You know what I mean? Like if I can take this into
my house and take possession of it, right? The fact that you
can't move land means no matter how much I own the land,
it's somewhat separate from me, right? It's not fully under my control.
You know, right? Like I mean, something's in my pocket, something's in
my locked house, that's like under my control. But this piece of
property, right? I mean, no, what happens if you're not around in
your land, somebody else comes and they squat and they have squatters'
rights and they contest your control and all these types of things,
you remain, there remains this gap between you and land that you
own as opposed you and chattel. So it seems to me that
by עבדים, Avadim, there's something nice that limiting it to קרקע Karka
and saying like not fully like property, not fully like a thing
that you own, there remains some type of a gap. So by
שמואל Shmuel saying that it is like מטלטלין, Mataltelin, right? If I
can take you by lifting you up, right? There's something very objectively
making you an object, dehumanizing about that. כסף Kesef and שטר Shtar
is something external that just says that I own you, right? And
even חזקה, Chazakah, we're going to see is you do a service
for me, but the service demonstrates a type of a relationship that
complete sense of ownership I think is more by the קניינים Kinyanim
that you do by מטלטלין. Mataltelin. So I think it's interesting that
the משנה Mishnah doesn't mention those קניינים Kinyanim and שמואל Shmuel does.
And the ברייתא Braisa tries to say everybody agrees, okay, but it's
a big חידוש, Chiddush, I think also how you conceptualize ownership of
slaves, how much you're making him like a piece of property. Yes.
You're saying
שמואל Shmuel wants to make him less?
I don't know if he wants to, but the result of שמואל
Shmuel saying that the קניינים Kinyanim of מטלטלין Mataltelin works by him
to me deepens that sense of the slave as property. Yes.
Right. So if you want to build this case that it's דומה
לקרקע Domeh le-karka to prevent total dehumanization, the theological basis, לי הארץ.
Li ha-aretz.
Right, that's a good point and right, I actually thought of that.
Right, כי גרים ותושבים אתם עמדי. Ki gerim ve-toshavim atem imadi. And
the גמרא's Gemara whole question that maybe it's חוזרת לבעלים ביובל. Chozeres
le-ba'alim be-yovel. Right, but in the end he doesn't, but that sense
that the land is never fully
yours, it's הקדוש ברוך הוא's.
Hakadosh Baruch Hu Right. The land is never fully yours. Exactly. Yes.
טוב. Tov.
I was going to say something similar to what you're saying, but
all object, movable objects on earth seem to be owned by somebody.
Oh, that's an interesting point.
So but land and people are different. Land is always there, there's
lots of unoccupied free land. Right.
That's an excellent point that I hadn't thought about. You're right. The
whole idea of, you know, Native Americans, like this idea that you
could own land, right? Land is God's, the earth is God's. But
you're right, like there's lots of land in this world that is
not owned. That's an excellent point. Okay, so yes.
But in the end anyway Shmuel says it is קניין משיכה. Kinyan
Meshicha. I understand, I'm pointing out the חידוש chiddush of Shmuel, okay?
It's a big jump from the משנה Mishna I think, I don't
think it's just a technical question. Anyway where does Shmuel get it
from? Right, the משנה Mishna says how you know that an עבד
כנעני Eved Kna'ani is נקנה nikneh by all these things from a
פסוק pasuk of of what do you call it of you know
והתנחלתם אותם לבניכם אחריכם. Ve-hitnachaltem otam livneichem achareichem.
Shmuel never tells me what his basis is. So Shmuel is like
a big חידוש. chiddush. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this,
ליתא דתניא. Leita detanya.
Now, the גמרא Gemara says like this, כיצד, Keitzad,
now what would be an example for let's look at Shmuel's statement
about how how משיכה Meshicha works? תקפו ובא אצלו קנאו קראו ובא
אצלו לא קנאו. Takfo u-va etzlo kna-o kara-o u-va etzlo lo kna-o.
So the גמרא Gemara says וקראו לו ve-kara-o lo if you call
him and he comes he doesn't that's not משיכה? Meshicha? But we
know it is משיכה Meshicha by animals. דתניא כיצד במסירה, De-tanya keitzad
be-mesira, how do you acquire an animal by handing over the reins,
that's what מסירה mesira is. אחזה בטלפה, Achaza be-tlapa, if you grabbed
it by its what's טלפה? tlapa? The hooves, thank you. בשערה be-se'ara
or the hair, which could mean the tail but Rashi says it
means like the hair by the head. באוכף שעליה, be-ukav she-aleha, the
saddle thank you.
בשליף שעליה, bi-shlif she-aleha, what's a שליף? shlif? A saddlebag.
בפרומביא שבפיה, be-pumbia she-be-piha, the bit what? Bit.
This is a load.
A load, okay, the bit in its mouth. בזוג שבצווארה ba-zug she-be-tzavara
in the bell around its neck. קנאה. kna-ah. So if you grabbed
hold of it by specifically by animals grabbing hold to a part
of the animal those is considered a קניין. kinyan. You might need
it to be handed over to you. Anyway כיצד במשיכה Keitzad be-meshicha
and how about drawing it to you? קרא לה והיא באה Kara
lah ve-hi ba-ah if you call it and it comes, או שהקישה
במקל o she-hikisha be-makel you hit it with a stick ורצה לפניו
ve-ratza le-fanav and it runs, כיון שעקר יד ורגל קנאה keivan she-akar
yad va-regel kna-ah once it lifted up a foot and and a
leg you acquired it, it moved like one foot one step. רבי
יאשיה ורבי יצחק ואמרי לה רבי יאשיה ואמרי לה רבי אחא Rabbi
Yoshiya ve-Rabbi Yitzchak ve-amri lah Rabbi Yoshiya ve-amri lah Rabbi Acha אמר
עד שתהלך לפניו מלא קומתה. amar ad she-tehalech le-fanav mlo komata. Anyway
you see that משיכה Meshicha works even if you call it and
it comes. So why is a slave different? So אמרי, Amri, so
here we get to a difference obviously for a slave. בהמה דעתה
דמרה אזלה, Behema da'atah de-marah azlah, animals don't have their own will.
So therefore if you're calling it's sort of instinctively automatically going you're
completely controlling it moving and it's going because of it's your דעת
da'at that's controlling it. So it's like you drew it. עבד דעתה
דנפשיה אזלה, Eved da'atah de-nafsheih azlah, the slave decides to listen to
you. So you know it might be that while he's a slave
he might not have a choice but it's still there's like a
decision, should I listen or not? So ultimately it's his decision and
therefore it does not demonstrate your full control. So here's the thing,
right, to turn him into an object if you call him and
he chooses to come he is still exhibiting his own subject personhood
so you can't acquire him as an object, right? To acquire him
as an object it would have to be that you completely objectify
him, you have to grab him and drag him, right, that shows
him as an object. But it's more dehumanizing that act, right, that's
my point. As long as he's demonstrating himself as a person with
the will and with a choice you're not acquiring him, right? רש"י
Rashi on the תורה Torah a couple of times says this like
maybe it was even this week's פרשה, parsha, קח את אהרן ואת
בניו. Kach et Aharon ve-et banav. So רש"י Rashi says what is
קח? kach? קחם בדברים Kachem bi-devarim means like you know talk to
them, have them, he says you're not take take them and like
drag them, like that makes them into an object. Okay but that's
what you have to do here.
That's what you have to do, which is again like the counterpoint
that we were saying before.
Right I understand, that that I think that there's a big חידוש
chiddush in Shmuel's move to try to use קניין מטלטלין kinyan metaltelin
here.
Okay, but they're unique considerations and circumstances, in other words how much
free will is it if he's in like you know being almost
forced?
I understand that was Michael's point, but you know I guess that's
the חידוש chiddush of the עבד Eved that any
demonstration, meaning any there's still always a choice, you know, even as
an עבד, Eved, you know, I mean so I think that that's
I understand I'm saying I think that that's like a nice point
that it's saying like that anything that you're not physically dragging him
we see him actually choosing even under that status of of being
a slave. Okay so the גמרא Gemara says אמר רב אשי עבד
קטן כבהמה דמי. Amar Rav Ashi eved katan ke-behema dami. Ah if
he's a minor then he's we don't really assume that he's choosing,
you know, then we assume it's more like instinctive and by a
minor if you call the minor slave it would work. Okay so
that's a big חידוש chiddush of Shmuel that משיכה Meshicha works. תנו
רבנן Tanu rabbanan כיצד בחזקה, keitzad be-chazakah, how does חזקה chazakah work
by a slave? Now חזקה chazakah by קרקע karka works by you
actually doing something to improve the קרקע karka and there's actually some
question if I do something like to get benefit from the קרקע
karka but I don't improve it that actually might not be an
act of חזקה chazakah which is interesting, right? Because you would think
if anything the owner is the one that gets the benefit like
you're going to hire people to work your land, right? But the
owner but anyway but somehow mastery by קרקע karka is demonstrated by
you like you're plowing it or fixing the fence or something of
that nature. Mastery by the slave, right? because that you know I
guess the master the owner... of ownership of land goes in two
ways. You improve the land that you own and you derive benefit.
But demonstrating your relationship to somebody as a slave, it's only in
one direction that the person does an act of sort of
servile service to you.
Wait, let's say like I... you just have to do an act
to me. Let's say I put a collar on him, wouldn't that?
Oh, that's an interesting point. Right, like you brand him as a
slave. You brand him as a slave. That's a good point. I
wonder. That's a good question.
I wonder if I'll have to check up if that is כיצד
בחזקה? keitzad b'chazakah? הנעלו, hin'ilo,
מנעלו. min'alo. So if he undid... if he helps you take your
shoes off, או הוליך כליו אחריו לבית המרחץ, o holich keilav acharav
l'veit hamerchatz, or he follows you afterwards with your like, your clothes
or whatever you need with you, your bathing implements to the bathhouse,
הפשיטו hifshito or
he helps you undress, הרחיצו hirchitzo or he bathes you, again we're
still in the bathhouse, סכו, sacho, it's so funny, all these descriptions
are in the bathhouse, right? He anoints you with oil, גרדו, gerado,
he scrapes you, הלבישו hilbisho or then after you're done with the
bath, he helps you get dressed again, הנעילו, hin'ilo, puts your shoe
back on. Okay, or so it's so funny, why all these bathhouse
things? Maybe because that's more servile, like to somebody else, the person
who's helping you in the bathhouse is like to somebody else who
can maybe be an attendant to you without being a slave.
Like if you help me out of the car?
I don't know, presumably any of those types of things. Okay. All
those... I understand, yeah, I don't know. I understand. I think any
of those types of things. It is an interesting question, like how
much, how servile would it have to be? Right, like let's say
you have him, I don't know, mow the lawn, right? Which is
a normal type of thing that you pay somebody to do. But
you could also have your slave mow the lawn. Yeah, I don't
know exactly. I mean my sense is it means any type of
a service, but it's also interesting that all these are also personal
services. Right? A lot of slaves you hire not as domestic, you
know, a lot of slaves were not domestic slaves. Okay. It's about
performing a slave...
No, that's the whole point.
The slave is doing a service to you. But the question we're
asking is, the examples are things that might be seen as דווקא
davka servile or דווקא davka personal. There are other forms of service
which are not personal or which are not servile. Would those be
included? הגביהו, higbiho, now if he lifted you up. I don't know
what that means. Lifted you, I don't know, onto the horse or
something. Any קנאו. k'nao. אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabi Shimon, לא תהא
חזקה גדולה מהגבהה, lo tehei chazakah gedolah mehagbahah, חזקה chazakah should not
be greater than הגבהה, hagbahah, שהגבהה קונה בכל מקום. shehagbahah konah b'chol
makom. הגבהה hagbahah works in all places. So מאי קאמר? mai ka'amar?
What's relevant? I don't know what's going on. אמר רב אשי, amar
Rav Ashi, here's what the
ברייתא braita means. הגביהו הוא לרבו קנאו. higbiho hu l'rabo k'nao. The
first הגביהו higbiho was a slave lifted the master up, like all
the things, the slave was doing a service for the master. הגביהו
רבו לו לא קנאו, higbiho rabo lo lo k'nao, but if he
lifted the slave, that would not work. אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabi
Shimon, לא תהא... lo tehei... Okay, because this is Shmuel, this is
תנאים, Tannaim, so this is before
Shmuel. Okay, so אמר רבי שמעון, amar Rabi Shimon, לא תהא חזקה
גדולה מהגבהה. lo tehei chazakah gedolah mehagbahah. I don't understand. Why should
חזקה chazakah work better than הגבהה? hagbahah? הגבהה קונה בכל מקום. hagbahah
konah b'chol makom. הגבהה hagbahah works in all other places. In all
places. Now of course this seems to exactly be the question of
Shmuel. Because הגבהה hagbahah works by מטלטלין, metaltelin, not by קרקע. karka.
So it seems like the תנא קמא tanna kamma is saying no,
it has to be חזקה, chazakah, and רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon is
saying ultimately what Shmuel said. If you lifted up the slave, that
should also work. That should be הגבהה, hagbahah, just like by all
מטלטלין metaltelin הגבהה hagbahah works. Okay. So it seems exactly this question
of does the קנינים kinyanim of מטלטלין metaltelin work, was not just
Shmuel, it was also רבי שמעון Rabi Shimon's response to this ברייתא.
braita.
Why didn't he say...
Yeah, I don't know why the גמרא Gemara did not do that.
That's correct, I don't know. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Now we're going to... this is going to be a
little bit of a challenge this next part. הא דאמרת הגביהו הוא
לרבו קנאו. ha d'amart higbiho hu l'rabo k'nao. Now that one of
the forms of חזקה chazakah is lifting the master up, assuming the
master wants to be lifted up. אלא מעתה שפחה כנענית תקנה בביאה?
ela me'atah shifchah K'na'anit tikneh b'viah?
Why not, going back to... now this is the question the גמרא
Gemara had once before by comparison by an אשה, ishah, קל וחומר,
kal v'chomer, and at the time we sort of said, well, it's
obviously different, like you know, that's, you know, one is about marriage
and intimacy and whatever, and this is about ownership. But of course
we cannot ignore the fact, which I think to me just comes
right to the surface in this discussion,
that female slaves often were taken sexual advantage of. Okay, so here
the גמרא Gemara just sort of says, oh okay, well, that's a
form of הגבהה. hagbahah. You're having sex, assuming the woman's on the
bottom, she's causing, you know, her body is making the master's body
off the ground, you know, be lifted up or whatever. Obviously it's
very technical. Let's call that a form of... and she's doing you
a service,
right? Talk about sexual advantage, right? Seeing that as a type of
a service that a slave does for a master. ההלכה, ha-halachah, it's
obviously forbidden. So let's call that הגבהה? hagbahah? תקנה בביאה? tikneh b'viah?
So the גמרא Gemara says, no. כי קאמרינן זה נהנה וזה מצטער.
ki amrinan zeh neheneh v'zeh mitzta'er. No, no, no. The normal
הגבהה hagbahah is when it causes a discomfort to the slave, like
it's not something the slave wants to be doing is lifting you
up. He'd rather not. הכא זה נהנה וזה נהנה. hacha zeh neheneh
v'zeh neheneh. Oh, here she gets pleasure. How do you know... assuming
that being raped... He's desiring to do it, right? So the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says, I know, I know, I know, I get it.
Well, maybe the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* doesn't want to go so far
to suggest rape as a form, of course. Why is suggesting this,
there's an איסור *Issur* of, right, even if she's willing there's an
איסור *Issur* doing. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says שלא כדרכה
מאי למימרא *shelo kedarka mai lemeimra*, let's say it's anal sex, and
therefore the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that that doesn't is not pleasurable
for the woman, that's the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*'s assumption. So that would
be a case of זה מצטער *ze mistaer*. אמר רבי חייא בר
אבא דמן ארכי מאן לימא לן דלאו הנאה אית להו *Amar Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba demin Archei man leima lan d'lav hana'ah it lehu*.
This rabbi, how do you know that they both don't have pleasure
in that act? והא משכבי אשה כתיב *Veha mishkevei isha ketiv*. And
also, it says משכבי אשה *mishkevei isha*, which is how we learn
that in כל התורה כולה *kol hatorah kullah*, anal sex is considered
like vaginal sex. הקישן הכתוב כדרכה לשלא כדרכה *Hikishan hakatuv kedarka leshelo
kedarka*. So if it doesn't work by vaginal, it shouldn't work by
anal. Okay, so that's how we exclude. Of course, the whole הוה
אמינא *hava amina* is very disturbing, and yes, also the fact that
it's ignoring the rape possibility.
Yes, it's getting as close to rape as possible with that suggestion.
Right. Exactly. רב יהודה הנדוא
Rav Yehuda
Hindua
*Rav Yehuda Handua*, now, yes, so he is from Hindu. Look at
רש"י Rashi *Rashi*. רב יהודה Rav Yehuda הנדוא *Rav Yehuda Handua* רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* says the first wide line at the bottom, מארץ כוש
*me'eretz Kush* or to be כושי *Kushi*, כוש מתרגמינן הנדוא *Kush metargeminan
Hindua*. Okay, so anyway, so this Hindu, this person from India, גר
ger שאין לו יורשים הוה *ger she'ein lo yorshim havah*. So he
was a convert who did not have any—what? Is Kush Ethiopia?
Kush is Ethiopia, but I'm assuming that it's being used for
any—Kush is that country down there and
it dips big
somewhere.
Yes, Kush is used as a place, not he's a Hindu, he's
a Hindu.
What?
Not Hindu, הנדוא
*Hindua* sounds like a place, not a religion. It's from India.
That's what I
said India.
From the Hindus, the land of the Hindus, is what they're saying.
I was assuming it was the Persian Empire.
Right, I know.
That's a good point. I was assuming that it was serving as
some generic name for a people, a place where people have darker
skin. But I don't know, what does your English say about that?
Does it say India?
It says Ethiopia. It says Ethiopia.
So הנדוא *Hindua* just is a word for Ethiopia according to that.
Okay, fine. Anyway, okay, so he was an Ethiopian. גר ger שאין
לו יורשים הוה *ger she'ein lo
yorshim havah*. He was a convert who had no heirs, he did
not have children after he had converted. חלש *chalash*, and he was
sick, meaning and he was on his deathbed. אמר מר זוטרא Mar
Zutra, לשיולי ביה *Amar Mar Zutra lish'ulei beih*. מר זוטרא Mar Zutra,
*Mar Zutra* went to ask after his well-being. חזאי *chazei*, so he
went to just pay a ביקור חולים *bikkur cholim* call, but you
know, sometimes he gets some there's some fringe benefit. Because חזאי דתקיף
ליה עלמא *chazei detakif leih alma*, he saw that he was about
to die. וטובא *utuva*, like he was very—really at the last, you
know, at
the—he's the עולם הבא *olam haba* has seized him, right? That's what
it means of the better world.
Oh, is that what it means? I thought it just—no, I thought
it just meant that this world was too much for him. It
is an interesting idiom, תקיף ליה עלמא *takif leih alma*, the world
has taken control, seized him too much. I thought it meant like
this world was getting to be too much for him. I don't
know. Anyway, whatever it means, it means he's on the verge of
death. Okay, so anyway, so what's going to happen? The גר ger
*ger* is going to die and he has no heir, so all
his property will be ownerless. Okay, what a great opportunity to be
around when that happens and then to seize all the property. So
the question is going to be a
fast one of mine.
Exactly. It's a fast one of mine, exactly, you know. So,
anyway. It's a fringe benefit, right? Anyway, so okay. The rabbi that
they say we're going to sign you on for a contract, $100,000,
Ferrari, and a brand new טלית *tallis*. No, I'll take everything, but
I won't take the טלית *tallis*. Why won't you take the טלית
*tallis*? Well, I have a policy, no fringe benefits. I'm just joking.
Okay, anyway.
All right. Anyway, so the point is that the slave though, if
he didn't seize the slave in advance, then once the גר ger
*ger* dies, then the slave becomes ownerless. You know who owns the
slave? The slave. He becomes free because he no longer has an
owner. So he needed to prevent that. So אמר ליה לעבדיה *amar
lei leavdeih*, so he said to the servant of this—the slave of
this רב Rav, יהודה הנדוא *Rav Yehuda Handua*, שלוף לי מסאני *shalof
li masanai*, you know, can you take my shoe off for me,
ואמטינהו לביתי *veamtinu leveiteih*, and bring it to my house. So therefore,
if in the time it would take to bring him to the
house will take twenty minutes, and he dies in the next twenty
minutes, as soon as this guy dies, the slave is in the
middle of doing this service, so I am in the middle of
doing this חזקה chazakah *chazakah* to the slave when he dies, so
he never has a moment of being free.
He starts the service when he was still owned by somebody else.
Yes, but after that it doesn't matter, as long as he's doing
the service at that critical moment, then I take possession of him.
איכא דאמרי Ika d'amri, *ika d'amrei*, some say גדול gadol, היה *gadol
hayah*. That he was an adult. The slave. זה פירש למיתה וזה
פירש לחיים *ze perosh lemisah veze perosh lachayim*. That when רב יהודה
הנדוא *Rav Yehuda Handua* dies, then he goes to life, which according
to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* means to life means he goes under the
control of the living, he transfers to the other person. ואיכא דאמרי
*ve'ika d'amrei*, some say—I'm
sorry, what—what does this mean?
When זה, when רב יהודה הנדוא died, okay, and מר זוטרא, Mar
Zutra, רש"י Rashi. says, goes to life, I would say the slave
transfers over to the control of the living person. Okay. The slave
did not have a choice. Now, you know, the slave doesn't get
to say if he wants to be controlled. The question, apparently the
point is if you are doing a חזקה chazakah on, well that's
going to be the question. Let's read the next line, okay, and
I'll tell you what תוספות Tosfos says. איכא דאמרי, ika d'amri some
say, קטן הוי, katan havei, he was a minor. Now רש"י's Rashi
גירסא girsa is ודלא כאבא שאול. u'delo k'Abba Shaul.
Everybody else has the גירסא girsa כאבא שאול, k'Abba Shaul, but we'll
read it like רש"י Rashi first.
A חזקה chazakah מרה. mara. Let me tell you a little secret.
Our גמרא Gemara, follows רש"י. Rashi Every time רש"י Rashi says הכי
גרסינן, hachi garsinan, and you look in the גמרא Gemara and you
say of course הכי גרסינן, hachi garsinan, that's what it's written here.
It's because the editor of the person who printed the גמרא Gemara
used רש"י's Rashi גירסא girsa to write this text. Okay, that's no
evidence that that's the standard text.
Often the standard text is otherwise and this is the way רש"י
Rashi edited it. Okay, ודלא כאבא שאול, u'delo k'Abba Shaul, not like
אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. דתניא גר שמת ובזו ישראל נכסיו, De'tanya ger
shemeis u'vizzu Yisrael nechasav,
if a גר ger, dies and then, you know, the ישראל Yisrael
sort of took, seized the property. והיו בניו עבדים בין גדולים בין
קטנים, Ve'hayu banav avadim bein gedolim bein ketanim,
and so there was here a gap. The גר ger died and
a day later it was seized by a ישראל. Yisrael. If there
were slaves, whether גדולים gedolim or קטנים, ketanim, קנו עצמן בני חורין,
kanu atzman benei chorin, they take possession of themselves because there was
this gap in time.
So he's already קנו kanu himself, right?
Because that was when there was a gap in time. In our
case there was no gap in time. But that's even a קטן
katan can be קונה koneh himself. A קטן katan is seen in
such possession of himself that even though normally we say a קטן
katan doesn't have a יד, yad, but at a deep level, you're
in possession of yourself even as a קטן. katan. So as soon
as the owner died, even as a קטן, katan, you owned yourself.
אבא שאול אומר, Abba Shaul omer, אבא שאול Abba Shaul says no.
גדולים קנו עצמן בני חורין. Gedolim kanu atzman benei chorin. That's true
by גדולים, gedolim, they have a יד, yad, so they can take
possession of themselves. קטנים, Ketanim, the minors, after their owner died, they
remained owned by nobody and they weren't able to possess themselves. And
in those cases, כל המחזיק בהם זכה בהם, kol hamachzik bahem zachah
bahem, anybody can take possession. So the reason the רש"י Rashi says
is איכא דאמרי ודלא כאבא שאול u'delo k'Abba Shaul is because if
it was a קטן katan and had you פסקנד paskened like אבא
שאול, Abba Shaul, you wouldn't have had to do this trick. Right,
you wouldn't have had to make sure you were possessing him at
that very second. There could be a gap in time. So why
did he have to do this trick to be possessing him at
the immediate moment? That's only not like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, that
even a קטן, katan, according to the חכמים, Chachamim, would be able
to possess himself. So therefore you had to be in possession of
him at that very second. That's the way רש"י reads it. תוספות
Tosfos and many other ראשונים Rishonim read it כאבא שאול, k'Abba Shaul,
and they say the opposite. They say, why do we have to
assume that he was doing this to ensure that the גר ger,
did not take possession of himself? He was doing this for another
reason. Even if the גר could, even if not the גר, even
if the עבד eved could take possession of himself, why would he
have wanted to have been having the עבד eved work for him
at the moment the guy died? So that somebody else didn't beat
him to taking possession of the slave. Okay. So therefore you don't
need to explain,
even according to אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, right? The גר couldn't have
taken, you know, the גר, you know, even in a קטן, katan,
even if the slave wouldn't go free, he would have wanted to
have been doing this so that nobody else would beat him to
it. So תוספות Tosfos says, so that's why it's like אבא שאול.
Abba Shaul. But תוספות Tosfos goes further and he says the following,
and he says no. When the גמרא Gemara in the end is
saying that it's a קטן katan and it's like אבא שאול, Abba
Shaul, it's saying like this, it's only a case of a קטן.
katan. Because if it were a case of a גדול, gadol, here's,
you might appreciate this, this might have been implicit in some of
your questions. If it were a case of a גדול, gadol even
if he was doing חזקה chazakah at the moment the guy died,
the גדול gadol, would still go free. At a deep level, right,
the idea that somebody fundamentally is in possession of themselves and it
reverts to that when the owner dies, right, even if I am
trying to do a חזקה chazakah exactly at that moment. This person's
ownership of themselves takes precedence over the חזקה that I am doing.
So therefore with the death of the master.
With the death of the master. So therefore if it was a
גדול, gadol it wouldn't have worked. If it's a קטן, katan,
like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, that's when it does work. The קטן
katan is not, cannot take possession of himself. And therefore the reason
he did it was so somebody else wouldn't beat him to the
punch, okay, and it only makes sense like a קטן katan like
אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. But in another, but if it was a
גדול Gadol, or if it wasn't like אבא שאול, Abba Shaul, then
the slave's possession of himself would take precedence over me possessing him
even at that moment.
Yeah. Wait, so this is what I'm understanding. So originally they were
קטנים, ketanim, right? Presumably. בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael went into ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and captured them, right? By taking from original inhabitants, right?
But what's the difference, so this guy gets himself free but now
I'm quote-unquote capturing him. In other words, why can't I do that?
Can't I just go and just capture him? They're my slave. Isn't
that the model?
Yeah, so that is a question of how does slavery, how does
it begin altogether? And in this case it has to do with
like כיבוש מלחמה kibbush milchama or whatever, but that's a case of
like, yes, of a violent, forceful possession. It's very different here that
he happens to be doing a service to me, you know. I
mean, and would it work if it wasn't in the context of
a war? Could I sneak into somebody's house and steal their babies
and then they make them my slave? I mean, no. I mean,
so look, that's obviously the deep disturbing thing is we're talking about
buying slaves, how did somebody get to be a slave in the
first place? Mostly it happens through war, okay, but it doesn't happen,
but not on an individual private basis, and here it was not
a forceful type of a possession, he was just doing a service.
But according to the הלכה, Halacha, I'm trying to understand this, like
you said about the כיבוש, Kibush, you know, at the time of
יהושע, Yehoshua, like a couple generations later, so I can't just capture
someone and make them my slave?
Right. I mean, can they owe me a debt, like you know,
a non-Jew, I can't capture someone
and make them my slave? Right. I mean, look, right. I think
I mean, I think that that I have to go back, that's
I think a סוגיא Sugya in גיטין Gittin or whatever about the
basic understanding is is that that happens through, look, if you're buying
from a non-Jew, I think then there's the question about how much
does that do we sort of set the rules for that or
that goes to how much like, you know, the non-Jewish country's gov
whatever recognizes what defines somebody a slave there, right? For us, I
think, I don't know, I'd have to go look at it again,
but the standard example is is that yes, is that something somebody
captured in the context in war, okay, not just like grab someone
and steal them. What happens if the government in which the non-Jewish
government that somebody can be taken as a slave for various reasons,
do I have to work- does it follow those rules and then
they're sold to me, right, that might be correct, I don't know,
I'd have to check again.
Yeah, well we spoke of free will as part of this aspect
of slaves, so what if the slave said to מר זוטרא, I
won't take the juice, my master's dying and I'm
going to be free in five? Right, exactly. He could have said
that. I mean, because yeah, he was מר זוטרא, he was רב
יהודה's slave, right? Now you know, it is so interesting that if
רב, the guy who was dying said, yes, list- do that for
him, then how much, you know, he's really doing it because of-
at the behest of his master. But I guess the point is,
well, after his master dies though, you know again, you don't sort
of look at... I do realize part of what's funny about this
is is that this act at the initial at the initial sort
of the beginning of the act was not about being a, you
know, owing a service to this person, it was doing it because
of the service to his other masters, so how the nature of
that act changes in midstream is very funny. Right, yeah. Right. Although,
you know, there obviously must have been a presumption, part of what
it means being a slave is my master has guests, I take
care of them whatever. But nevertheless, it wasn't done as a in
terms of a slave relationship to this guy. So and then that
changes in midstream.
Yeah, and there's a slight hint that it's at least תוספות, Tosafot,
it's sort of like a קידושין Kiddushin situation, let's say it was
a גדול, שמא יקדמנו אחר.
shemma
yikadmenu acher.
Well, that I was thinking about that, yeah.
That- right, and then she's קונה עצמה koneh atzmah when he dies.
Okay, בקונה את עצמו בכסף. Bekoneh et atzmo b'kesef. Now we get
to the complicated case in the משנה Mishnah about who owns the
money and who's doing the קנין כסף. kinyan kesef. בכסף על ידי
אחרים, Bekesef al yedei acherim,
so other people's money, according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. רש"י says,
בכסף על ידי אחרים אין, bekesef al yedei acherim in, other people's
money yes, אבל לא על ידי עצמו, aval lo al yedei atzmo,
he can't give his own money. במה עסקינן? Bimai askinan? Now what's
the case? This is according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אילימא שלא
מדעתו, Ileima shelo midato, that other people are paying the money and
they have not asked the slave if he wants to be freed,
so and then that's when it works. מכדי, Michti, שמעינן ליה לרבי
מאיר, shamian leh le'Rabbi Meir, we know רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds,
דאמר חוב הוא לעבד שיצא מיד רבו לחירות, d'amar chov hu l'eved
sheyeitzei miyad rabo l'cheirut, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says you can't say
זכין zachin by freeing a slave. A slave might not want to
be freed. Okay, there are more restrictions on him as a non-slave
and so on. So the classic example of that is I write
a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur and I say- my slave isn't around
and I say to Michael, Michael, accept this שטר שחרור shtar shichrur
on behalf of my slave. So normally we say זכין לאדם שלא
בפניו, zachin l'adam shelo befanav, you can do something for somebody's behalf,
but רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it doesn't work, that's not necessarily
in the slave's best interest.
So he's also not be Jewish and- and he's
also not be Jewish, he wants to have a lot of, yeah
right, sexual opportunity, whatever it might be. Okay, so therefore, he wants
to eat תרומה, Terumah, whatever case might be if he's if he's
owned by a כהן. Kohen. So according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
if the when it's not a case of a שטר, shtar, somebody
is paying the master to free the slave. Did they ask the
slave? So according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, if they didn't ask
the slave it doesn't work, you can't do free a slave with
a if he doesn't want it, okay? I mean, now by the
way, that's not true. A third party cannot free the slave, the
master can give the slave a שטר שחרור, shtar shichrur, the slave
doesn't have to agree, right? It's בעל כרחו, bal korcho, it could
be בעל כרחו, bal korcho, but a third party cannot be part
of that if the slave has not agreed. Okay, so אילימא שלא
מדעתו, ileima shelo midato,
he has no security by the master- yeah, exactly.
מכדי שמעינן ליה לרבי מאיר דאמר חוב הוא לעבד שיצא מיד רבו
לחירות, Michti, shamian leh le'Rabbi Meir d'amar chov hu l'eved sheyeitzei miyad
rabo l'cheirut, that it's a detriment, it's not necessarily to the slave's
benefit. דתניא, Detanya, and we taught, זכין לאדם שלא בפניו ואין חבין
לאדם אלא בפניו. zachin l'adam shelo befanav ve'ein chavin l'adam ela befanav.
You can do something that clearly is to somebody's benefit even if
they're not around but not if it's to their detriment.
So therefore, he's not even around, wouldn't make a difference, as long
as he doesn't want-
right, it's not just around, he has to agree to it. So
if a third party is giving the money, it can only be
if the slave agrees according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. אלא פשיטא
מדעתו, Ella p'shita midato, it must be that the slave is agreeing
to this. והא קמשמע לן, V'ha kamashma lan, בכסף על ידי אחרים
אין, bekesef al yedei acherim in, and even so only a third
party can give the money. אדידך עצמו לא, Adidech atzmo lo, he
can't give the money. אלמא, Alma, so what's the- why could he
not give the money? Here he is, he wants to be freed,
the third party's doing it, let him give the money. אלמא אין
קנין לעבד בלא רבו, Alma ein kinyan le'eved belo rabo, there's no
way a slave according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir could own money
without his master owning it.
Presumably, presumably. Right. We'll see more about this, but yes. Okay, so
that explains why it has to be a third party. אי הכי
אימא סיפא. I hachi eima seifa. So now we understood כסף על
ידי אחרים. Kesef al yedei acherim. The slave wants it, he can't
own his own money, other people have to provide the money. Now
let's get to the next line. Okay, ובשטר על ידי עצמו, Uveshtar
al yedei atzmo, but you can give the שטר shtar directly to
the עבד. eved. Now, does it mean if we let's take the
משנה כפשוטו, mishna kepshuto, it means only to the עבד. eved. על
ידי עצמו אין, Al yedei atzmo in, it sounds like only to
the עבד, eved, על ידי אחרים לא, al yedei acherim lo, not
to others. ואם מדעתו, Ve'im midato, but if he agrees to be
freed, because that's the context of other people giving the money for
him, על ידי אחרים אמאי לא? al yedei acherim amai lo? Why
not give it to a third party? If I'm agreeing to be
freed, you can then it's זכין, zachin, then you can give it
to a third party. Okay, so we don't understand why you can't
give the שטר shtar to a third party. וכי תימא מאי על
ידי עצמו אף על ידי עצמו. Vekhi teima mai al yedei atzmo
af al yedei atzmo. Ah, so maybe when it says שטר על
ידי עצמו, shtar al yedei atzmo, it means even to him, which
would make sense. The money has to come from a third party
when he agrees, the שטר shtar could be either to a third
party or to him. That would make sense. So what's the חידוש
chiddush that the שטר shtar could go to him? והא קמשמע לן
דגיטו וידו באים כאחד. Veha kamashma lan degito veyado ba'im ke'echad. Because
it makes a lot of sense. Since רבי מאיר's Rebbi Meir whole
reason that he can't give money is that he has no ownership
on his own, so how do you give him a שטר? shtar?
How does he own the שטר? shtar? Anything you give him, it's
like the master took it from his right hand and put it
in his left hand. If the slave is an extension of the
master's יד, yad, so how do you give- so he can't own
money, so how could you give him a שטר? shtar? Ah, גיטו
וידו באים כאחד gito veyado ba'im ke'echad in the moment that he
gets freed, so at the same time he becomes his own domain.
Okay. So that explains the beginning of the משנה. mishna. והא
לא תניא הכי, Veha lo tanya hachi, but the ברייתא brayta teaches
not that way, that that's not what רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said.
Okay, so again רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir is
saying, this gets a little confusing, right, רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says,
so okay רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir says
כסף על ידי אחרים, kesef al yedei acherim, so we say that
that's מדעתו, midato, because we say that you can't have a third
party doing it according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir without it being
מדעתו midato because רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir said it's a חוב לעבד.
chov la'eved. Okay, שטר על ידי עצמו, shtar al yedei atzmo, so
we want to say that now we want to say that means
אף על ידי עצמו, af al yedei atzmo, okay, אף. af. Okay,
so it means, so we want to say what that means is,
since we're talking about מדעתו midato here, let's put this here. כסף
על ידי אחרים, kesef al yedei acherim, we've decided that everything therefore
means מדעתו, midato, okay, because that otherwise אחרים acherim would not work,
because you can only use a third party if it's מדעתו. midato.
So שטר על ידי עצמו shtar al yedei atzmo means עצמו atzmo
plus אחרים. acherim. Okay, this works because of זכין, zachin, or whatever
just because he's agreeing, because he's agreeing, and this works because of
גיטו וידו באים כאחד. gito veyado ba'im ke'echad. Okay, גיטו וידו. gito
veyado. So the חידוש chiddush is, even though he doesn't have his
own money, he can take his own שטר. shtar. But certainly other
people can take the שטר shtar for him. Okay, and all of
this is
מדעתו. midato. That would be a nice read of the משנה, mishna,
but the משנה mishna says הא לא תניא הכי, ha lo tanya
hachi, but the ברייתא brayta doesn't teach that way. דתניא, Detanya, we
talk about ברייתא, brayta, בשטר על ידי עצמו ולא על ידי אחרים,
דברי רבי מאיר. beshtar al yedei atzmo velo al yedei acherim, divrei
Rebbi Meir. Not על ידי אחרים. al yedei acherim. So only על
ידי עצמו. al yedei atzmo. So what sense does this make? Why
can the שטר shtar only be על ידי עצמו? al yedei atzmo?
As long as it's מדעתו, midato, and it has to be מדעתו
midato because else you wouldn't somebody else wouldn't be able to give
the money because it's a חוב לעבד. chov la'eved. So let somebody
else take the שטר shtar for him. Why can only he be
the one that takes the שטר? shtar? Okay, so that's שליחות, shlichus,
no?
Maybe, right, he can't make someone a שליח shliach for him.
So that makes like a possibility that maybe even if it's mida-
but but then you get to the question about how the כסף
על ידי אחרים kesef al yedei acherim works. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says, אמר אביי לעולם שלא מדעתו. Amar Abbaye le'olam shelo midato.
You know what? We were wrong. Even though it's a חוב, chov,
כסף kesef still works שלא מדעתו. shelo midato. Why? ושני כל כסף
הואיל וקני ליה בעל כרחו מקני ליה בעל כרחו. Veshanai kol kesef,
ho'il vekanileh be'al korcho, maktileh be'al korcho.
Since a slave is sold by money against his will, he can
be freed by money against his will, which there's a certain logic.
I can purchase this slave from his master without the slave agreeing,
so I can purchase his freedom from his master without the slave
agreeing. Okay, so that's the logic, alright? You're not so sure. Okay,
anyway, that's Abbaye's argument. Okay, אי הכי i hachi says the גמרא,
Gemara שטר נמי. shtar nami. So he's sold by a שטר, shtar,
let him be freed by a שטר shtar even with a third
party. No, האי שטר לחוד והאי שטר לחוד. hai shtar lachud vehai
shtar lachud. No, no, no. One שטר shtar is a שטר shtar
sale, the other שטר shtar is a שטר shtar of freedom, of
manumission. So they're fundamentally different processes, because a שטר shtar always makes...
is clear, the nature of the act. Money, the same money that's
used to free him could be used to transfer his ownership. So
therefore fundamentally that act is seen as what? It could work exactly
to transfer ownership, it might as well work to free him.
But שטר אחרים shtar acheirim does not work because of why?
Because because that needs to be
מדעתו. m'daato. Because it's a חוב לעבד. chov la'eved. You cannot have
a third party involved unless it's to his benefit. With the exception
of כסף, kesef, because by a כסף, kesef, a third party could
have purchased him, so a third party can free him.
A third party could have purchased him through שטר shtar too, no?
But that would have been a different שטר, shtar, that's exactly, you
just now went through exactly what the גמרא Gemara said.
If a third party frees him at the, by purchasing him, right,
doesn't it still imply that he has to have the consent of
the slave to free him, just as in the case of the
first?
No, you don't need the consent of the slave. The master can
free his slave against the slave's will. It's only getting you write
a שטר שחרור shtar shichrur whether the slave likes it or not.
It's only to do with involve a third party that you need
the slave's will, okay? The slave can be freed against his will,
but you can't get a third party involved against the will of
the slave, okay? So the גמרא gemara says, so כסף הכי נמי
האי כספא לחוד והאי כספא לחוד. kesef hachi nami hai kaspa lachud
vehai kaspa lachud. So what? So it's different money. No, טיבעא מחד
הוא. tiva mi'chad hu. It's all the same money, okay? So basically,
so אביי Abaye says, and רבא Rava is going to say the
same thing, this is actually שלא מדעתו. shelo m'daato. It's שלא מדעתו.
shelo m'daato. So שלא מדעתו, shelo m'daato, so you can't still can't
do כסף על ידי עצמו, kesef al yedei atzmo, he doesn't own
his own money. שטר Shtar can only be על ידי עצמו al
yedei atzmo because that's the idea, you can, you can free a
slave against his will. You can't give the שטר shtar to somebody
else against his will because why can another person represent the slave
against the slave's will? But the חידוש chiddush is that somebody can
buy his freedom against his will. Why? The same way somebody could
have purchased him against his will, he can buy his freedom against
his will. That's what אביי Abaye says. שטר Shtar is different. A
שטר shtar sale is fundamentally different from a
שטר shtar of freedom. רבא אמר, Rava amar, רבא Rava agrees to
the read of the ברייתא, Baraita, he gives a different explanation why
money is different. כסף קבלת רבו גרמה לו שטר קבלת אחרים גרמה
לו. kesef kabbalat rabbo garma lo shtar kabbalat acheirim garma lo. רבא
Rava says who's doing the act? In this case, a third party
pays the money. But the act of freedom comes by the master
accepting the money. So you don't say normally the principle of you
don't say זכין zachin when it's שלא מדעתו shelo m'daato is you're
not allowed to represent me if I don't want you to represent
me. But if somebody paid money, if you paid money to free
me, you're not representing me. The master taking money is the act
of freeing. So what you did to provide the money, that's being
as not fundamentally the act of freeing. The act of freeing is
the taking of the money, okay? So therefore you don't need the
principle of זכין. zachin. But to give a שטר shtar to a
third party, the party who receives the שטר shtar makes a lot
of sense. The party who receives, who normally receives the שטר? shtar?
The עבד. eved. So if you're going to receive the שטר shtar
for the עבד, eved, that's only if you represent the עבד eved
and if you say that it's not a זכות, z'chus, only if
the עבד eved wants you to represent him. So the שטר, shtar,
you need to be מדעת העבד. m'daat ha'eved. כסף Kesef fundamentally the
master is the act of freeing is the accepting of the money,
so nobody has to represent the עבד eved and therefore it can
work even שלא מדעתו. shelo m'daato.
So שטר אחרים shtar acheirim would work, is that what you're saying?
If it is מדעתו, m'daato, then שטר אחרים shtar acheirim would work,
right. But it's שלא מדעתו shelo m'daato and even so כסף אחרים
kesef acheirim works, either because it might as well just have been
a sale or fundamentally in the case of כסף kesef nobody has
to represent the slave. So therefore it works שלא מדעתו, shelo m'daato,
whereas by שטר, shtar, the recipient has to represent the slave. Okay,
so that is רב מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now we move on to
the חכמים. Chachamim.
Nevertheless, as you know, what we said before still applies that if
the, if a מום mum goes free, then I can't recapture him
so to speak, yes.
The חכמים אומרים כסף על ידי עצמו. Chachamim omrim kesef al yedei
atzmo. The רבנן Rabbanan disagree and they say he can have his
own money, okay. So before we get to the whole זכין zachin
issue, now we're dealing with this idea, can a slave have his
own money? And the רבנן Rabbanan say it's possible and therefore he
can redeem himself with his own money. But כסף על ידי עצמו,
kesef al yedei atzmo, אין על ידי אחרים לא? in al yedei
acheirim lo? Are we to is this to suggest only with his
own money and somebody else's money no? אמאי, Amai, why? נהי נמי
דשלא מדעתו, nihei nami deshelo m'daato, we said that even if we
said the משנה Mishnah is that the slave isn't aware, doesn't even
want it. But מיכדי שמענו להו לרבנן michdi shamnu lehu lerabbanan or
let's say at least isn't aware, we know the רבנן Rabbanan say
דאמרי זכות הוא שיצא מתחת יד רבו לחירות, d'amrei z'chus hu sheyeitzei
mitachat yad rabbo lachirut, that it's a זכות z'chus for the slave
to be free and people can operate on the slave's behalf. דתנינא
זכין לאדם שלא בפניו וחבין לו אלא בפניו. d'tanina zachin l'adam shelo
b'fanav v'chavin lo ela b'fanav. So why can't it be other people's
money? So the גמרא says וכי תימא מאי על ידי עצמו אף
על ידי עצמו, v'chei teima mai al yedei atzmo af al yedei
atzmo, which is probably the פשט. p'shat. Yes, of course it works
על ידי אחרים, al yedei acheirim, but it even works his own
money because it's possible for a slave to have money. וקמשמע
לן דיש קנין לעבד בלא רבו. v'kamashma lan d'yesh kinyan l'eved b'lo
rabbo. Okay, that's a reasonable read. אי הכי אימא סיפא בשטר על
ידי אחרים ולא על ידי עצמו. ei hachi eima seifa b'shtar al
yedei acheirim velo al yedei atzmo. Okay, so now the
רבנן Rabbanan say, right, the רבנן Rabbanan say, so this is here,
so we have כסף kesef and שטר, shtar, okay? So רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says כסף kesef is אחרים acherim and שטר shtar is
עצמו. atzmo. So כסף kesef is אחרים acherim why? Because slave can't
have money. Slave can't have money. And שטר shtar is על ידי
עצמו al yidei atzmo and על ידי אחרים al yidei acherim because
it's a... and therefore and all this is שלא מדעתו shelo mada'ato
so nobody else can do it. So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is
דוקא davka על ידי אחרים al yidei acherim דוקא davka על ידי
עצמו, al yidei atzmo, right? That's רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. The חכמים
Chachamim say כסף על ידי עצמו kesef al yidei atzmo.
and
שטר, shtar, what did they say and the חכמים Chachamim say אחרים.
acherim. Okay, the exact flip of רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Now...
all right,
we'll worry about that in a minute. Okay. כסף kesef על ידי
עצמו al yidei atzmo why? Because a slave can own money. A
slave can own money. Okay. Okay, that's what it means. Now, we're
saying, but wait a minute, other people should also be able to
give because the חכמים Chachamim say that it's a זכות. zechus. And
anyway even רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who says it's a חוב chov
allows other people to give money. Okay. So עצמו atzmo means even
עצמו atzmo plus אחרים. acherim. Okay. Now if this is עצמו atzmo
plus אחרים acherim because obviously other people could give the money as
well, the חידוש chiddush is that he can own money. When this
was אחרים, acherim, it must mean only אחרים, acherim, right? Yes? Because
if this meant עצמו atzmo and אחרים acherim and this meant אחרים
acherim and עצמו atzmo then they'd be saying the same thing. So
this must mean only אחרים. acherim. So only אחרים, acherim, why can't
you give a שטר shtar directly to the slave? Okay, so the
גמרא says... okay... the גמרא says אי הכי ei hachi
אימא סיפא eima seifa
בשטר beshtar על ידי אחרים al yidei acherim ולא על ידי עצמו.
velo al yidei atzmo. Presumably it means only אחרים. acherim. But we
hold גיטו וידו באים כאחד. gito veyado ba'im ke'echad. Why not? You
can give a שטר shtar directly to a slave and גיטו וידו
באים כאחד. gito veyado ba'im ke'echad. And if you want to say...
what, על ידי אחרים al yidei acherim אף על ידי אחרים. af
al yidei acherim.
This means even על ידי אחרים. al yidei acherim. Okay. So then
they both work for both. So that's true... אף על ידי אחרים...
af al yidei acherim... but we hold that שזכות לעבד שיצא מיד
רבו לחירות. shezechus la'eved sheyeitzei miyad rabo lacheirus. That
even על ידי אחרים al yidei acherim it can work. אי הכי
ei hachi and it's a זכות zechus so somebody else can do
it. נינוינהו וניתנינהו nenvin'hu venisninhu just wrap them together. בכסף ובשטר בין
על ידי אחרים בין על ידי עצמו. bekesef ubeshtar bein al yidei
acherim bein al yidei atzmo. So we've got a problem how to
read this. אלא ella בכסף bekesef בין על ידי אחרים בין על
ידי עצמו. bein al yidei acherim bein al yidei atzmo. Okay, you're
right. כסף kesef we said is even עצמו, atzmo, he can own
money. Certainly אחרים acherim because it's a זכות. zechus. That's like we
said. בשטר beshtar על ידי אחרים al yidei acherim ולא על ידי
עצמו. velo al yidei atzmo. But you know what, this is only
על ידי אחרים. al yidei acherim. That actually there's a position that
says you cannot
give the שטר shtar directly to the slave. Why? Because you do
not say גיטו וידו באים כאחד. gito veyado ba'im ke'echad. He cannot
actually take possession of the שטר, shtar, which is ironic because if
he can own money and give money and then you can't say
גיטו וידו gito veyado it's very very strange. Okay. Anyway, but let's
take... so רש״י Rashi actually says... well whatever. So let's just read
it. The גמרא says... ורבי שמעון היא. veRabbi Shimon hi. We'll just
get to the end of the... of the דף. daf. ורבי שמעון
בן אלעזר היא דתניא רבי שמעון בן אלעזר אומר אף בשטר על
ידי אחרים ולא על ידי עצמו. veRabbi Shimon ben Elazar hi detanya
Rabbi Shimon ben Elazar omer af beshtar al yidei acherim velo al
yidei atzmo. ושלש מחלוקות בדבר. veshalosh machlokos badavar. There's a three-way debate
about this. So there's a whole question of רש״י Rashi exactly lining
up the debate. I'll just say that because it is very strange
that he could have his own money and not give him... and
not give him a שטר. shtar. רש״י Rashi actually says... well whatever.
So רש״י Rashi actually says the רבנן Rabbanan here does mean אחרים
acherim and עצמו, atzmo, that the rabbis actually say that both work
for both. But that the reason it's framed here in saying only
אחרים acherim was to sort of allude to this third position of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So רש״י Rashi actually says the חכמים Chachamim
themselves are not endorsing רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Okay. So there's a
couple of different issues here. One is by the כסף... kesef there's
one, the question is: is it זכין zachin or not זכין zachin
to allow other people to be involved? Another question is: can the
slave own money? רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says a slave can't own
money, it has to be other people's money. The חכמים Chachamim say
a slave can own money. Okay, that's one issue. Okay, the other
issue is by the שטר: shtar: can you say גיטו וידו באים
כאחד? gito veyado ba'im ke'echad? Which is a similar question of: can
the slave even in the act of freeing him have his own
sense of property and ownership. So there's three real issues here. One
is whether we say זכין zachin or חוב, chov, okay? Where חכמים
Chachamim say זכין zachin and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says חוב. chov.
And the... the biggest נפקא מינא nafka mina about this would be
a case about שטר על ידי אחרים. shtar al yidei acherim. Okay,
that's one debate. The other is a question about: does he own
money? So does he own, can't own, can't own, okay? Where, right,
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says can't own and the חכמים Chachamim say
he can, he can own money.
And right, and
that's a question about saying כסף kesef... על ידי עצמו. al yidei
atzmo And then there's a third question about גיטו וידו באים כאחד.
gito veyado ba'im ke'echad.
Okay, וידו, veyado, you know, and that... and that would be the
question about שטר על ידי עצמו. shtar al yidei atzmo. Okay, so
those are the three debates however you exactly line them up. A
שטר על ידי אחרים shtar al yidei acherim is a question about
זכין zachin or חוב. chov. Can somebody represent him in receiving the
שטר? sh'tar? The גמרא says somebody giving money doesn't have to really
represent him, that you don't need זכין. zakhin. But to receive a
שטר sh'tar on his behalf you need זכין. zakhin. Can he own
or not own money?
It's not a זכות.
zakhut. Right. Can he own or not own money is can he
give his own money, is that even possible for him to give
his own money? And can you give a שטר sh'tar directly to
him is גיטו וידו באים כאחד. gito v'yado ba'im k'echad. Yes.
Does the עבד eved own the shirt on his back? What?
No. Okay, I just want to turn the page. I know we're
two minutes over, but I need to turn the page for my
own sake so we're not more than an עמוד amud behind. אמר
רבא מאי טעמא דרבי שמעון בן אלעזר? Amar Rava mai ta'ama d'Rabbi
Shimon ben Elazar? Why does רבי שמעון בן אלעזר Rabbi Shimon ben
Elazar say you can't give him a שטר sh'tar directly? גמר לה
למה מאשה, Gamar lah lamma me'ishah, he learns from the גט get
of a woman. מאי אשה עד שיוציא גט לרשות שאינו שלו, Mai
ishah ad sheyotzi get l'reshut she'eino shelo, when you give the גט
get to the woman, you're giving it to outside, the owner's giving
it outside of his control. The woman is a different entity than
him. Okay. She's כגופו k'gufo though. What? I understand. Okay, anyway, no,
but if you look at רש"י it says yes, but nevertheless the
woman is not the property of the husband to the same degree.
I'll discuss this more tomorrow. Okay, but the woman is not the
property of the husband, so he gives it to somebody who is
not his property. אף עבד נמי עד שיוציא גט לרשות שאינו שלו,
Af eved nami ad sheyotzi get l'reshut she'eino shelo, so the גט
get has to be given to somebody who is not his property,
it can't be given to the slave, okay, although there is an
aspect of גיטו וידו gito v'yado but it's not to the same
degree. Okay, and I guess we will end here, so we didn't
really turn the page, but anyway.